A Guide to the Celia Thaxter Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6994-d
Celia Thaxter Collection 1872-1894
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6994-d
49 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research
Acquisition Information
Deposit 1967 Mar 8
Item Listing
- Manscripts
  - Poem, " Beethoven ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "God help us to be grateful.. .", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Four line verse seeking the grace to find God's love despite life's trials.]
  - Poem, " In Tuscany ", [Oct 1884]; TMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Only thyself can harm.. .", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [One verse, apparently a quotation from longer work.]
  - Poem, " Out Soldiers ", n. d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, " Song ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Single line, "The sunrise never failed us yet.", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Twilight ", n. d.; AMs, 2 p.
- Letters
  - Celia Thaxter, Newtonville, to Mrs. Houghton, 1872 Jan 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Regrets missing call and being unable to accept invitation; hopes to see her in Cambridge. ]
  - Celia Thaxter, Newtonville, to Dear Sir, 1883 Feb 2; ALS, 3 p.
    [Expresses appreciation for book and note; comments on favorite poems in the volume "
    Daphles
    , " "
    Wife of Brittany
    A Summer Moon
    , " and "
    Feudal Picture
    . "]
  - Celia Thaxter, Appledore, to [James Ripley] Osgood, 1873 n.m. 22; ALS, 4 p.
    [Comments positively on Mr. Anthony's engravings; suggests their placement in the book; requests 100 copies for her brothers; speculates on sales.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Boston, to Miss Eliot, 1875 Dec 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Gives permission to use her poems; apologizes for delay in responding.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Appledore, to [James Ripley] Osgood, 1876 Mar 5; ALS, 2 p.
    [Wants Mr. Fields advice before making selection from the Shoals volume; feels remote from everything; wishes her novel were written.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Shoals, to Mr. Oakes, 1877 Jul 9; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for flattering note and newspaper article on her work; hopes to meet him soon.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Appledore, to [Hjalmar Hjorth] Boyesen, 1879 Aug 2; ALS, 1 p.
    [Comments on his bright cheerfulness; thanks him for the charming letter.]
  - Celia Thaxter, [ Isle of Shoals], to Dr. Richard Derby, 187, Thursday; ALS, 1 p.
    [Invites him and his sister to visit; writes that she will paint something in his book of poems; invites Mrs. Heard in postscript.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Appledore, to Mrs Houghton, 1880 Apr 30; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks her for dinner invitations; explains her delay in responding; regrets being unable to accept.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Appledore, Isle of Shoals, to [ Houghton Mifflin], 1880 Aug 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Rejects "vulgar cover"; requests something simpler.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Shoals, to Mr. Baker, 1881 Aug 16; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for vase and for his charming thoughtfulness.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Kittery Point, Maine, to [Horace P.] Chandler, 1882 Jan 5; ALS, 1 p.
    [Comments on printer's errors in her poems, giving example for "
    Stardust
    "; considers them inconsequential as they will soon, and deservedly, be forgotten.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Winthrop House, to Mr. Miles, 1882 Oct 21; ALS, 1 p.
    [Introduces Miss Blake who has question he is better able to answer.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Boston, to Mrs. Nixon, 1885 Oct 25; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends a copy of poems with photograph, autograph, and additional photo.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Boston, to Mr. Gentry, 1886 Mar 8; ALS, 1 p.
    [Gives permission to use poems; sends photograph and signature.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Clifford [Hotel, Boston?], to Mrs. Allen, 1886 Dec 25; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks her and her son for Christmas gifts; encloses note to Marion.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Appledore, Isle of Shoals, to Mr. Amery, 1887 Jun 20; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends pledges; requests certificates be sent; states mail arrives four times a day.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Hotel Clifford, [ Boston], to Dear Friend, 1888 Jan 20; ALS, 1 p.
    [Asks him to return the enclosed [poem ?] if it is unwanted; understands he has "a ton of poems on hand."]
  - Celia Thaxter, Clifford [Hotel, Boston?], to [Horace P.] Chandler, 1888 Feb 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for photo; comments on Mrs. Dickinson's beauty and charm.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Appledore, Isle of Shoals, to Dear Madam, 1888 Sep 29; ALS, 1 p.
    [Gives publishing history of "
    Don't Sing Before Breakfast
    , " first printed in "
    Wide Awake
    " then in a volume of children's poems, and "
    Courage
    , " printed in
    Atlantic Monthly
    and then in her first volume of poems; states that they are available in bookstores if she is interested.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Portsmouth, to S. S. McClure, 1890 Feb 2; ALS, 1 p.
    [Declines invitation to write something because of poor health; encloses magazine photo.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Portsmouth, to Mr. Allen, 1890 Nov 27; ALS, 1 p.
    [States she sent poems without accompanying letter; requests their return if they cannot be used; writes that she will try again if he would like something different.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Shoals, to Mr. Jamison, 1891 May 31; ALS, 1 p.
    [States she has written "the gentleman from the far West" a note indicating he will find the song on page 60 of
    Driftwood
    . ]
  - Celia Thaxter, Portsmouth, to Mr. Munroe, 1891 Oct 29; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for hospitality shown the Hassams of whom she is very fond; sends regards to Miss Phinney.]
  - Childe Hassam, New York, to Mr. Munroe, [ Lexington, Massachusetts?], 1891 Nov 6; ALS, 2 p.
    [Compares sea air to Lexington air; "votes" for Lexington air at present; describes frames and prices received for his work in New York; inquires about Lexington friends Miss Phinney, Miss Shaw, and Miss [Grokin].]
  - Celia Thaxter, Portsmouth, to [Richard Watson] Gilder, [editor, Century ], 1893 Mar 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Offers piece for the
    Century
    to use if possible, as supporters of the [noble maid] for the Republic's emblem who want to be able to state they are quoting from the largest, most important magazine.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Appledore, Isle of Shoals, to Horace P. Chandler, Boston, 1893 Jun 7; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Sends copy of a piece and permission to print it if Houghton & Mifflin agree; mentions health and weather.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Shoals, to [Horace P.] Chandler, 1894 Apr 2; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for the photograph; praises its loveliness.]
  - Celia Thaxter, Shoals, to [Horace P.] Chandler, 1894 Jul 30; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for pictures; comments on his kindness for making them available to people who want them.]
  - Celia Thaxter to Edmund Clarence Stedman, ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Introduces Ross Turner; sends regards to Mrs. S[tedman].]
- Photographs and engravings
  - Celia Thaxter, head and shoulders, 1892; Photo
    [Signed, with ANS, n. d., requesting return if not desired.]
  - Magazine photo, Celia Thaxter, seated, 1890 Sep 12; Photo
    [With ANS, 1 page, 1890 Sep 12, stating that this is the only photograph available.]
  - Celia Thaxter, profile, n. d.; Engraving
    [In youth.]
  - Celia Thaxter, profile, n. d.; Engraving
    [Signed, older.]
  - Magazine page of The Cottage Hearth, vol. V no. 10, with engraving of Celia Thaxter, head and shoulders, 1878 Oct; Page(incomplete)
    [Includes biographical piece.]
  - 2 photos of Celia Thaxter's cottage, n. d.; Photos
  - Landing at Appledore, Photo
  - Celia Thaxter's parlor, n. d.; Photo
  - View from Celia Thaxter's garden gate, n. d.; Photo
- Miscellaneous
  - Check, 1871 Jun 22
    [Endorsed on back.]
  - Printed booklet containing poem, " The Singer of the Sea, " by Ina D. Coolbrith, 1894 Dec; Booklet
    [In memory of Celia Thaxter, published by the Century Club of California. ]